<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>misinformation on ovdixon</title>
    <link>https://ovdixon.com/tags/misinformation/</link>
    <description>ovdixon (misinformation)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2020 14:12:24 +1000</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://ovdixon.com/tags/misinformation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Tackling COVID-19 Misinformation through Design 🔎 </title>
      <link>https://ovdixon.com/posts/community-coping/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2020 14:12:24 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ovdixon.com/posts/community-coping/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;inspiration&#34;&gt;Inspiration&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;echo.jpg&#34;
         alt=&#34;Christophe Vorlet @nytimes&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Christophe Vorlet @nytimes&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The COVID-19 outbreak and response has been accompanied by an overabundance of rapidly spreading information and misinformation. Prompting the World Health Organisation to announce that we are not only facing a pandemic but also an ‘infodemic’. The angst generated by this deluge of (mis)information can have detrimental effects on the social and emotional wellbeing of individuals and communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;ideation&#34;&gt;Ideation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trying to wipe out misinformation is an impossible task. So as a group we reframed the problem; how could we improve the capacity of communities to better cope with the alienating effects of misinformation. We undertook an iterative process leading to a final concept:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A community-based platform that facilitates users in sharing strategies to cope with the impacts of COVID-19 misinformation and mandated lockdowns.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Users can discover coping strategies by swiping through a Tinder-esque card stack of community generated suggestions. Cards are presented as short, 25 word or less descriptions of a partiular coping strategy (e.g. “I have started a veggie garden on my balcony”). While swiping through the card stack users can save a particular coping strategy which resonates with them. Cards are filtered in the stack based on popularity i.e. the number of saves. Users are incentivised to submit their own suggestions with weekly prizes. This not only drives user engagement with the app, but also is an attractive opportunity for marketers to connect with savvy digital natives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;implementation&#34;&gt;Implementation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The web application was developed as a static website with front-end code. It was developed in this way more as a proof of concept with the opportunity to develop the backend at a later stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;demo.gif&#34;
         alt=&#34;Demo of scanning a passport into the app (running on iPad Pro 11)&#34; width=&#34;90%&#34;/&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Demo of scanning a passport into the app (running on iPad Pro 11)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;challenges&#34;&gt;Challenges&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was my first iOS project so I had some difficulty with Xcode but overall enjoyed the experience of coding in Swift. Because the app  processes sensitive passport information, I had to consider data privacy and protection. All data processed is stored locally on device, however the app would benefit from adding password protection. The app should adhere to GDRP laws as there is a legal basis for providing passport data to immigration services.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>