<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>fishing on ovdixon</title><link>https://ovdixon.com/tags/fishing/</link><description>ovdixon (fishing)</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 14:12:24 +1000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ovdixon.com/tags/fishing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Teaching my iPhone to recognise fish species 🐠</title><link>https://ovdixon.com/posts/fish-classification/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 14:12:24 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://ovdixon.com/posts/fish-classification/</guid><description>&lt;p>Fishing has always been a hobby of mine. To ensure the sustainiblity of recreational fish stocks it is important that fisherman are able to recognise different fish species and recall size restrictions / bag limits. I thought this application could help new anglers identify the fish they catch.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="collecting-images">Collecting Images&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I decided to train a model able to recognise five of the most common recreational fish species caught along the East Coast of Australia; bream, whiting, flathead, luderick and whiting.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>
&lt;img src="species.png"
alt="Three of the five species"/> &lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Three of the five species&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;p>Using the command line tool Instaloader I scraped images from public instagram hashtags under each species (i.e #sandwhiting) I scraped 1000+ images for each species, then went through and filtered out the best images totalling a minimum of 250.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>
&lt;img src="instaloader.png"
alt="Using Instaloader in command line"/> &lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Using Instaloader in command line&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="training-on-createml">Training on CreateML&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>This is Apple&amp;rsquo;s no-code computer vision training tool optimised for use with iOS. You simply drag and drop a collection of class folders to begin training. My training data totalled 1,288 over 5 classes.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>
&lt;img src="training.png"
alt="Training took a number of hours on my i5 Macbook Air"/> &lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Training took a number of hours on my i5 Macbook Air&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="testing">Testing&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I tested the model on 10 unseen images across the 5 species classes. Results were suprising, 10/10 accurate classifications.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>
&lt;img src="testing.png"
alt="Accurate even when the fish is angled to the camera"/> &lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Accurate even when the fish is angled to the camera&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="deployment">Deployment&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I deployed the model to my iPhone 12 Pro using a public project called &lt;a href="https://github.com/shu223/MLModelCamera">MLModelCamera&lt;/a>. It allows for Drag-and-Drop testing of Core ML models.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>
&lt;img src="deployment.png"
alt="I haven&amp;amp;rsquo;t had a chance to test it live on a fishing trip, will update the post hence."/> &lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>I haven&amp;rsquo;t had a chance to test it live on a fishing trip, will update the post hence.&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure></description></item><item><title>Fishing Licence Onboarding Redesign 🎣</title><link>https://ovdixon.com/posts/fishing-licence/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 14:12:24 +1000</pubDate><guid>https://ovdixon.com/posts/fishing-licence/</guid><description>&lt;h4 id="inspiration">Inspiration&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>The current process of purchasing a recreational fishing licence online in NSW violates several principles of visual, navigation, and interaction design.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="ideation">Ideation&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>I sought to develop an alternative web-based (mobile &amp;amp; desktop) onboarding process for purchasing a fishing licence. I began with some user profiles to understand who would be using the site. Fishing attracts a diverse range of people of all ages. It is important that the licence onboarding be an accessible lightweight experience focused on efficiency.&lt;/p>
&lt;figure>
&lt;img src="sketch.png"
alt="Initial annotated sketches"/> &lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Initial annotated sketches&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>
&lt;img src="wireframe.png"
alt="Next came low fidelity wireframes"/> &lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Next came low fidelity wireframes&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;figure>
&lt;img src="mockup.png"
alt="Finally mockups developed using Adobe XD"/> &lt;figcaption>
&lt;p>Finally mockups developed using Adobe XD&lt;/p>
&lt;/figcaption>
&lt;/figure>
&lt;h4 id="implementation">Implementation&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>It was developed from the ground up using HTML, CSS and JS Several features, including a progress bar and sticky navigation, were designed to give the user a greater sense of control.&lt;br>
I received the following feedback from the marker: &amp;ldquo;You scoped this project excellently! Good use of code, only minor mistakes and consistent styling and use of javascript. The website itself was excellently done.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Check it out live at: &lt;a href="https://odix8891.github.io/deco-1016-website/">https://odix8891.github.io/deco-1016-website/&lt;/a>&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>